<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<XMLBIBLE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" biblename="ENGLISH_GNBDC">
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="50" bname="Philippians">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">From Paul and Timothy, servants of Christ Jesus — To all God's people in Philippi who are in union with Christ Jesus, including the church leaders and helpers:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">May God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ give you grace and peace.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">I thank my God for you every time I think of you;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">and every time I pray for you all, I pray with joy</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">because of the way in which you have helped me in the work of the gospel from the very first day until now.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">And so I am sure that God, who began this good work in you, will carry it on until it is finished on the Day of Christ Jesus.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">You are always in my heart! And so it is only right for me to feel as I do about you. For you have all shared with me in this privilege that God has given me, both now that I am in prison and also while I was free to defend the gospel and establish it firmly.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">God is my witness that I am telling the truth when I say that my deep feeling for you all comes from the heart of Christ Jesus himself.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">I pray that your love will keep on growing more and more, together with true knowledge and perfect judgement,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">so that you will be able to choose what is best. Then you will be free from all impurity and blame on the Day of Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Your lives will be filled with the truly good qualities which only Jesus Christ can produce, for the glory and praise of God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I want you to know, my brothers and sisters, that the things that have happened to me have really helped the progress of the gospel.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">As a result, the whole palace guard and all the others here know that I am in prison because I am a servant of Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">And my being in prison has given most of the brothers and sisters more confidence in the Lord, so that they grow bolder all the time to preach the message fearlessly.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Of course some of them preach Christ because they are jealous and quarrelsome, but others from genuine goodwill.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">These do so from love, because they know that God has given me the work of defending the gospel.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">The others do not proclaim Christ sincerely, but from a spirit of selfish ambition; they think that they will make more trouble for me while I am in prison.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">It does not matter! I am happy about it — so long as Christ is preached in every way possible, whether from wrong or right motives. And I will continue to be happy,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">because I know that by means of your prayers and the help which comes from the Spirit of Jesus Christ I shall be set free.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">My deep desire and hope is that I shall never fail in my duty, but that at all times, and especially just now, I shall be full of courage, so that with my whole being I shall bring honour to Christ, whether I live or die.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">For what is life? To me, it is Christ. Death, then, will bring more.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">But if by continuing to live I can do more worthwhile work, then I am not sure which I should choose.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">I am pulled in two directions. I want very much to leave this life and be with Christ, which is a far better thing;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">but for your sake it is much more important that I remain alive.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">I am sure of this, and so I know that I will stay. I will stay on with you all, to add to your progress and joy in the faith,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="26">so that when I am with you again, you will have even more reason to be proud of me in your life in union with Christ Jesus.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="27">Now, the important thing is that your way of life should be as the gospel of Christ requires, so that, whether or not I am able to go and see you, I will hear that you are standing firm with one common purpose and that with only one desire you are fighting together for the faith of the gospel.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="28">Don't be afraid of your enemies; always be courageous, and this will prove to them that they will lose and that you will win, because it is God who gives you the victory.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="29">For you have been given the privilege of serving Christ, not only by believing in him, but also by suffering for him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="30">Now you can take part with me in the battle. It is the same battle you saw me fighting in the past, and as you hear, the one I am fighting still.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="2">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Your life in Christ makes you strong, and his love comforts you. You have fellowship with the Spirit, and you have kindness and compassion for one another.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">I urge you, then, to make me completely happy by having the same thoughts, sharing the same love, and being one in soul and mind.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Don't do anything from selfish ambition or from a cheap desire to boast, but be humble towards one another, always considering others better than yourselves.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">And look out for one another's interests, not just for your own.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">The attitude you should have is the one that Christ Jesus had: and took the nature of a servant. He became like a human being and appeared in human likeness. his death on the cross. and gave him the name that is greater than any other name. will fall on their knees, to the glory of God the Father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">He always had the nature of God, but he did not think that by force he should try to remain equal with God. all beings in heaven, on earth, and in the world below</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">Instead of this, of his own free will he gave up all he had,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">He was humble and walked the path of obedience all the way to death —</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">For this reason God raised him to the highest place above</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">And so, in honour of the name of Jesus</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">and all will openly proclaim that Jesus Christ is Lord,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">So then, dear friends, as you always obeyed me when I was with you, it is even more important that you obey me now while I am away from you. Keep on working with fear and trembling to complete your salvation,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">because God is always at work in you to make you willing and able to obey his own purpose.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">Do everything without complaining or arguing,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">so that you may be innocent and pure as God's perfect children, who live in a world of corrupt and sinful people. You must shine among them like stars lighting up the sky,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">as you offer them the message of life. If you do so, I shall have reason to be proud of you on the Day of Christ, because it will show that all my effort and work have not been wasted.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">Perhaps my life's blood is to be poured out like an offering on the sacrifice that your faith offers to God. If that is so, I am glad and share my joy with you all.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">In the same way, you too must be glad and share your joy with me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">If it is the Lord's will, I hope that I will be able to send Timothy to you soon, so that I may be encouraged by news about you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">He is the only one who shares my feelings and who really cares about you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">All the others are concerned only with their own affairs, not with the cause of Jesus Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">And you yourselves know how he has proved his worth, how he and I, like a son and his father, have worked together for the sake of the gospel.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">So I hope to send him to you as soon as I know how things are going to turn out for me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">And I trust in the Lord that I myself will be able to come to you soon.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">I have thought it necessary to send you our brother Epaphroditus, who has worked and fought by my side and who has served as your messenger in helping me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="26">He is anxious to see you all and is very upset because you had heard that he was ill.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="27">Indeed he was ill and almost died. But God had pity on him, and not only on him but on me, too, and spared me an even greater sorrow.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="28">I am all the more eager, then, to send him to you, so that you will be glad again when you see him, and my own sorrow will disappear.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="29">Receive him, then, with joy, as a brother in the Lord. Show respect to all such people as he,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="30">because he risked his life and nearly died for the sake of the work of Christ, in order to give me the help that you yourselves could not give.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="3">
			<VERS vnumber="1">In conclusion, my brothers and sisters, be joyful in your union with the Lord. I don't mind repeating what I have written before, and you will be safer if I do so.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Watch out for those who do evil things, those dogs, those who insist on cutting the body.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">It is we, not they, who have received the true circumcision, for we worship God by means of his Spirit and rejoice in our life in union with Christ Jesus. We do not put any trust in external ceremonies.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">I could, of course, put my trust in such things. If anyone thinks they can trust in external ceremonies, I have even more reason to feel that way.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">I was circumcised when I was a week old. I am an Israelite by birth, of the tribe of Benjamin, a pure-blooded Hebrew. As far as keeping the Jewish Law is concerned, I was a Pharisee,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">and I was so zealous that I persecuted the church. As far as a person can be righteous by obeying the commands of the Law, I was without fault.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">But all those things that I might count as profit I now reckon as loss for Christ's sake.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Not only those things; I reckon everything as complete loss for the sake of what is so much more valuable, the knowledge of Christ Jesus my Lord. For his sake I have thrown everything away; I consider it all as mere refuse, so that I may gain Christ</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">and be completely united with him. I no longer have a righteousness of my own, the kind that is gained by obeying the Law. I now have the righteousness that is given through faith in Christ, the righteousness that comes from God and is based on faith.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">All I want is to know Christ and to experience the power of his resurrection, to share in his sufferings and become like him in his death,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">in the hope that I myself will be raised from death to life.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I do not claim that I have already succeeded or have already become perfect. I keep striving to win the prize for which Christ Jesus has already won me to himself.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">Of course, my brothers and sisters, I really do not think that I have already won it; the one thing I do, however, is to forget what is behind me and do my best to reach what is ahead.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">So I run straight towards the goal in order to win the prize, which is God's call through Christ Jesus to the life above.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">All of us who are spiritually mature should have this same attitude. But if some of you have a different attitude, God will make this clear to you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">However that may be, let us go forward according to the same rules we have followed until now.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">Keep on imitating me, my brothers and sisters. Pay attention to those who follow the right example that we have set for you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">I have told you this many times before, and now I repeat it with tears: there are many whose lives make them enemies of Christ's death on the cross.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">They are going to end up in hell, because their god is their bodily desires. They are proud of what they should be ashamed of, and they think only of things that belong to this world.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">We, however, are citizens of heaven, and we eagerly wait for our Saviour, the Lord Jesus Christ, to come from heaven.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">He will change our weak mortal bodies and make them like his own glorious body, using that power by which he is able to bring all things under his rule.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="4">
			<VERS vnumber="1">So then, my brothers and sisters, how dear you are to me and how I miss you! How happy you make me, and how proud I am of you! This then, dear brothers and sisters, is how you should stand firm in your life in the Lord.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Euodia and Syntyche, please, I beg you, try to agree as sisters in the Lord.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">And you too, my faithful partner, I want you to help these women; for they have worked hard with me to spread the gospel, together with Clement and all my other fellow-workers, whose names are in God's book of the living.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">May you always be joyful in your union with the Lord. I say it again: rejoice!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Show a gentle attitude towards everyone. The Lord is coming soon.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">Don't worry about anything, but in all your prayers ask God for what you need, always asking him with a thankful heart.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">And God's peace, which is far beyond human understanding, will keep your hearts and minds safe in union with Christ Jesus.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">In conclusion, my brothers and sisters, fill your minds with those things that are good and that deserve praise: things that are true, noble, right, pure, lovely, and honourable.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">Put into practice what you learnt and received from me, both from my words and from my actions. And the God who gives us peace will be with you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">In my life in union with the Lord it is a great joy to me that after so long a time you once more had the chance of showing that you care for me. I don't mean that you had stopped caring for me — you just had no chance to show it.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">And I am not saying this because I feel neglected, for I have learnt to be satisfied with what I have.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I know what it is to be in need and what it is to have more than enough. I have learnt this secret, so that anywhere, at any time, I am content, whether I am full or hungry, whether I have too much or too little.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I have the strength to face all conditions by the power that Christ gives me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">But it was very good of you to help me in my troubles.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">You Philippians know very well that when I left Macedonia in the early days of preaching the Good News, you were the only church to help me; you were the only ones who shared my profits and losses.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">More than once when I needed help in Thessalonica, you sent it to me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">It is not that I just want to receive gifts; rather, I want to see profit added to your account.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">Here, then, is my receipt for everything you have given me — and it has been more than enough! I have all I need now that Epaphroditus has brought me all your gifts. They are like a sweet-smelling offering to God, a sacrifice which is acceptable and pleasing to him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">And with all his abundant wealth through Christ Jesus, my God will supply all your needs.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">To our God and Father be the glory for ever and ever! Amen.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">Greetings to each one of God's people who belong to Christ Jesus. The brothers and sisters here with me send you their greetings.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">All God's people here send greetings, especially those who belong to the Emperor's palace.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">May the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with you all.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="56" bname="Titus">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">From Paul, a servant of God and an apostle of Jesus Christ. I was chosen and sent to help the faith of God's chosen people and to lead them to the truth taught by our religion, May God the Father and Christ Jesus our Saviour give you grace and peace.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">which is based on the hope for eternal life. God, who does not lie, promised us this life before the beginning of time,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">and at the right time he revealed it in his message. This was entrusted to me, and I proclaim it by order of God our Saviour.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">I write to Titus, my true son in the faith that we have in common.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">I left you in Crete, so that you could put in order the things that still needed doing and appoint church elders in every town. Remember my instructions:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">an elder must be blameless; he must have only one wife, and his children must be believers and not have the reputation of being wild or disobedient.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">For since a church leader is in charge of God's work, he should be blameless. He must not be arrogant or quick-tempered, or a drunkard or violent or greedy for money.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">He must be hospitable and love what is good. He must be self-controlled, upright, holy, and disciplined.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">He must hold firmly to the message which can be trusted and which agrees with the doctrine. In this way he will be able to encourage others with the true teaching and also to show the error of those who are opposed to it.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">For there are many, especially converts from Judaism, who rebel and deceive others with their nonsense.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">It is necessary to stop their talk, because they are upsetting whole families by teaching what they should not, and all for the shameful purpose of making money.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">and no longer hold on to Jewish legends and to human commandments which come from people who have rejected the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Everything is pure to those who are themselves pure; but nothing is pure to those who are defiled and unbelieving, for their minds and consciences have been defiled.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">They claim that they know God, but their actions deny it. They are hateful and disobedient, not fit to do anything good.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="2">
			<VERS vnumber="1">But you must teach what agrees with sound doctrine.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Instruct the older men to be sober, sensible, and self-controlled; to be sound in their faith, love, and endurance.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">In the same way instruct the older women to behave as women should who live a holy life. They must not be slanderers or slaves to wine. They must teach what is good,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">in order to train the younger women to love their husbands and children,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">to be self-controlled and pure, and to be good housewives who submit to their husbands, so that no one will speak evil of the message that comes from God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">In the same way urge the young men to be self-controlled.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">In all things you yourself must be an example of good behaviour. Be sincere and serious in your teaching.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Use sound words that cannot be criticized, so that your enemies may be put to shame by not having anything bad to say about us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">Slaves are to submit to their masters and please them in all things. They must not answer them back</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">or steal from them. Instead, they must show that they are always good and faithful, so as to bring credit to the teaching about God our Saviour in all they do.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">For God has revealed his grace for the salvation of the whole human race.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">That grace instructs us to give up ungodly living and worldly passions, and to live self-controlled, upright, and godly lives in this world,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">as we wait for the blessed Day we hope for, when the glory of our great God and Saviour Jesus Christ will appear.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">He gave himself for us, to rescue us from all wickedness and to make us a pure people who belong to him alone and are eager to do good.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Teach these things and use your full authority as you encourage and rebuke your hearers. Let none of them look down on you.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="3">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Remind your people to submit to rulers and authorities, to obey them, and to be ready to do good in every way.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Tell them not to speak evil of anyone, but to be peaceful and friendly, and always to show a gentle attitude towards everyone.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">For we ourselves were once foolish, disobedient, and wrong. We were slaves to passions and pleasures of all kinds. We spent our lives in malice and envy; others hated us and we hated them.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">But when the kindness and love of God our Saviour was revealed,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">he saved us. It was not because of any good deeds that we ourselves had done, but because of his own mercy that he saved us, through the Holy Spirit, who gives us new birth and new life by washing us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">God poured out the Holy Spirit abundantly on us through Jesus Christ our Saviour,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">so that by his grace we might be put right with God and come into possession of the eternal life we hope for.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">This is a true saying. I want you to give special emphasis to these matters, so that those who believe in God may be concerned with giving their time to doing good deeds, which are good and useful for everyone. God's grace be with you all.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">But avoid stupid arguments, long lists of ancestors, quarrels, and fights about the Law. They are useless and worthless.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">Give at least two warnings to those who cause divisions, and then have nothing more to do with them.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">You know that such people are corrupt, and their sins prove that they are wrong.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">When I send Artemas or Tychicus to you, do your best to come to me in Nicopolis, because I have decided to spend the winter there.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">Do your best to help Zenas the lawyer and Apollos to get started on their travels, and see to it that they have everything they need.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">Our people must learn to spend their time doing good, in order to provide for real needs; they should not live useless lives.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">All who are with me send you greetings. Give our greetings to our friends in the faith.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="57" bname="Philemon">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">From Paul, a prisoner for the sake of Christ Jesus, and from our brother Timothy — To our friend and fellow-worker Philemon,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">and the church that meets in your house, and our sister Apphia, and our fellow-soldier Archippus:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">May God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ give you grace and peace.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">Brother Philemon, every time I pray, I mention you and give thanks to my God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">For I hear of your love for all God's people and the faith you have in the Lord Jesus.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">My prayer is that our fellowship with you as believers will bring about a deeper understanding of every blessing which we have in our life in union with Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">Your love, dear brother, has brought me great joy and much encouragement! You have cheered the hearts of all God's people.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">For this reason I could be bold enough, as your brother in Christ, to order you to do what should be done.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">But because I love you, I make a request instead. I do this even though I am Paul, the ambassador of Christ Jesus, and at present also a prisoner for his sake.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">So I make a request to you on behalf of Onesimus, who is my own son in Christ; for while in prison I have become his spiritual father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">At one time he was of no use to you, but now he is useful both to you and to me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I am sending him back to you now, and with him goes my heart.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I would like to keep him here with me, while I am in prison for the gospel's sake, so that he could help me in your place.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">However, I do not want to force you to help me; rather, I would like you to do it of your own free will. So I will not do anything unless you agree.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">It may be that Onesimus was away from you for a short time so that you might have him back for all time.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">And now he is not just a slave, but much more than a slave: he is a dear brother in Christ. How much he means to me! And how much more he will mean to you, both as a slave and as a brother in the Lord!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">So, if you think of me as your partner, welcome him back just as you would welcome me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">If he has done you any wrong or owes you anything, charge it to my account.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">Here, I will write this with my own hand: I, Paul, will pay you back. (I should not have to remind you, of course, that you owe your very self to me.)</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">So, my brother, please do me this favour for the Lord's sake; as a brother in Christ, cheer me up!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">I am sure, as I write this, that you will do what I ask — in fact I know that you will do even more.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">At the same time, get a room ready for me, because I hope that God will answer the prayers of all of you and give me back to you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">Epaphras, who is in prison with me for the sake of Christ Jesus, sends you his greetings,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">and so do my fellow-workers Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">May the grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with you all.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="62" bname="1  John">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">We write to you about the Word of life, which has existed from the very beginning. We have heard it, and we have seen it with our eyes; yes, we have seen it, and our hands have touched it.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">When this life became visible, we saw it; so we speak of it and tell you about the eternal life which was with the Father and was made known to us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">What we have seen and heard we announce to you also, so that you will join with us in the fellowship that we have with the Father and with his Son Jesus Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">We write this in order that our joy may be complete.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Now the message that we have heard from his Son and announce is this: God is light, and there is no darkness at all in him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">If, then, we say that we have fellowship with him, yet at the same time live in the darkness, we are lying both in our words and in our actions.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">But if we live in the light — just as he is in the light — then we have fellowship with one another, and the blood of Jesus, his Son, purifies us from every sin.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">If we say that we have no sin, we deceive ourselves, and there is no truth in us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">But if we confess our sins to God, he will keep his promise and do what is right: he will forgive us our sins and purify us from all our wrongdoing.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">If we say that we have not sinned, we make God out to be a liar, and his word is not in us.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="2">
			<VERS vnumber="1">I am writing this to you, my children, so that you will not sin; but if anyone does sin, we have someone who pleads with the Father on our behalf — Jesus Christ, the righteous one.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">And Christ himself is the means by which our sins are forgiven, and not our sins only, but also the sins of everyone.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">If we obey God's commands, then we are sure that we know him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">Those who say that they know him, but do not obey his commands, are liars and there is no truth in them.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">All those who obey his word are people whose love for God has really been made perfect. This is how we can be sure that we are in union with God:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">those who say that they remain in union with God should live just as Jesus Christ did.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">My dear friends, this command I am writing to you is not new; it is the old command, the one you have had from the very beginning. The old command is the message you have already heard.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">However, the command I am now writing to you is new, because its truth is seen in Christ and also in you. For the darkness is passing away, and the real light is already shining.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">Those who say that they are in the light, yet hate their brothers and sisters, are in the darkness to this very hour.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">Those who love their brothers and sisters live in the light, and so there is nothing in them that will cause someone else to sin.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">But those who hate their brothers and sisters are in the darkness; they walk in it and do not know where they are going, because the darkness has made them blind.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I am writing to you, my children, because your sins are forgiven for the sake of Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I am writing to you, fathers, because you know him who has existed from the beginning. I am writing to you, young people, because you have defeated the Evil One.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">I am writing to you, my children, because you know the Father. I am writing to you, fathers, because you know him who has existed from the beginning. I am writing to you, young people, because you are strong; the word of God lives in you, and you have defeated the Evil One.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Do not love the world or anything that belongs to the world. If you love the world, you do not love the Father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">Everything that belongs to the world — what the sinful self desires, what people see and want, and everything in this world that people are so proud of — none of this comes from the Father; it all comes from the world.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">The world and everything in it that people desire is passing away; but those who do the will of God live for ever.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">My children, the end is near! You were told that the Enemy of Christ would come; and now many enemies of Christ have already appeared, and so we know that the end is near.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">These people really did not belong to our fellowship, and that is why they left us; if they had belonged to our fellowship, they would have stayed with us. But they left so that it might be clear that none of them really belonged to us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">But you have had the Holy Spirit poured out on you by Christ, and so all of you know the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">I am writing to you, then, not because you do not know the truth; instead, it is because you do know it, and you also know that no lie ever comes from the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">Who, then, is the liar? It is those who say that Jesus is not the Messiah. Such people are the Enemies of Christ — they reject both the Father and the Son.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">For all those who reject the Son also reject the Father; those who accept the Son have the Father also.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">Be sure, then, to keep in your hearts the message you heard from the beginning. If you keep that message, then you will always live in union with the Son and the Father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">And this is what Christ himself promised to give us — eternal life.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="26">I am writing this to you about those who are trying to deceive you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="27">But as for you, Christ has poured out his Spirit on you. As long as his Spirit remains in you, you do not need anyone to teach you. For his Spirit teaches you about everything, and what he teaches is true, not false. Obey the Spirit's teaching, then, and remain in union with Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="28">Yes, my children, remain in union with him, so that when he appears we may be full of courage and need not hide in shame from him on the Day he comes.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="29">You know that Christ is righteous; you should know, then, that everyone who does what is right is God's child.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="3">
			<VERS vnumber="1">See how much the Father has loved us! His love is so great that we are called God's children — and so, in fact, we are. This is why the world does not know us: it has not known God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">My dear friends, we are now God's children, but it is not yet clear what we shall become. But we know that when Christ appears, we shall be like him, because we shall see him as he really is.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Everyone who has this hope in Christ keeps himself pure, just as Christ is pure.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">Whoever sins is guilty of breaking God's law, because sin is a breaking of the law.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">You know that Christ appeared in order to take away sins, and that there is no sin in him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">So everyone who lives in union with Christ does not continue to sin; but whoever continues to sin has never seen him or known him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">Let no one deceive you, my children! Whoever does what is right is righteous, just as Christ is righteous.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Whoever continues to sin belongs to the Devil, because the Devil has sinned from the very beginning. The Son of God appeared for this very reason, to destroy what the Devil had done.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">None of those who are children of God continue to sin, for God's very nature is in them; and because God is their Father, they cannot continue to sin.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">This is the clear difference between God's children and the Devil's children: all who do not do what is right or do not love others are not God's children.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">The message you heard from the very beginning is this: we must love one another.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">We must not be like Cain; he belonged to the Evil One and murdered his own brother Abel. Why did Cain murder him? Because the things he himself did were wrong, but the things his brother did were right.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">So do not be surprised, my brothers and sisters, if the people of the world hate you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">We know that we have left death and come over into life; we know it because we love our brothers and sisters. Whoever does not love is still under the power of death.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">All who hate others are murderers, and you know that murderers have not got eternal life in them.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">This is how we know what love is: Christ gave his life for us. We too, then, ought to give our lives for our brothers and sisters!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">Rich people who see a brother or sister in need, yet close their hearts against them, cannot claim that they love God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">My children, our love should not be just words and talk; it must be true love, which shows itself in action.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">This, then, is how we will know that we belong to the truth; this is how we will be confident in God's presence.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">If our conscience condemns us, we know that God is greater than our conscience and that he knows everything.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">And so, my dear friends, if our conscience does not condemn us, we have courage in God's presence.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">We receive from him whatever we ask, because we obey his commands and do what pleases him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">What he commands is that we believe in his Son Jesus Christ and love one another, just as Christ commanded us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">Those who obey God's commands live in union with God and God lives in union with them. And because of the Spirit that God has given us we know that God lives in union with us.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="4">
			<VERS vnumber="1">My dear friends, do not believe all who claim to have the Spirit, but test them to find out if the spirit they have comes from God. For many false prophets have gone out everywhere.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">This is how you will be able to know whether it is God's Spirit: anyone who acknowledges that Jesus Christ came as a human being has the Spirit who comes from God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">But anyone who denies this about Jesus does not have the Spirit from God. The spirit that he has is from the Enemy of Christ; you heard that it would come, and now it is here in the world already. God is love, and those who live in love live in union with God and God lives in union with them.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">But you belong to God, my children, and have defeated the false prophets, because the Spirit who is in you is more powerful than the spirit in those who belong to the world.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Those false prophets speak about matters of the world, and the world listens to them because they belong to the world.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">But we belong to God. Whoever knows God listens to us; whoever does not belong to God does not listen to us. This, then, is how we can tell the difference between the Spirit of truth and the spirit of error.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">Dear friends, let us love one another, because love comes from God. Whoever loves is a child of God and knows God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Whoever does not love does not know God, for God is love.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">And God showed his love for us by sending his only Son into the world, so that we might have life through him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">This is what love is: it is not that we have loved God, but that he loved us and sent his Son to be the means by which our sins are forgiven.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Dear friends, if this is how God loved us, then we should love one another.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">No one has ever seen God, but if we love one another, God lives in union with us, and his love is made perfect in us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">We are sure that we live in union with God and that he lives in union with us, because he has given us his Spirit.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">And we have seen and tell others that the Father sent his Son to be the Saviour of the world.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">If anyone declares that Jesus is the Son of God, he lives in union with God and God lives in union with him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">And we ourselves know and believe the love which God has for us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">Love is made perfect in us in order that we may have courage on Judgement Day; and we will have it because our life in this world is the same as Christ's.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">There is no fear in love; perfect love drives out all fear. So then, love has not been made perfect in anyone who is afraid, because fear has to do with punishment.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">We love because God first loved us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">If we say we love God, but hate our brothers and sisters, we are liars. For people cannot love God, whom they have not seen, if they do not love their brothers and sisters, whom they have seen.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">The command that Christ has given us is this: all who love God must love their brother or sister also.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="5">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Whoever believes that Jesus is the Messiah is a child of God; and whoever loves a father loves his child also.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">This is how we know that we love God's children: it is by loving God and obeying his commands.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">For our love for God means that we obey his commands. And his commands are not too hard for us,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">because every child of God is able to defeat the world. And we win the victory over the world by means of our faith.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Who can defeat the world? Only the person who believes that Jesus is the Son of God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">Jesus Christ is the one who came with the water of his baptism and the blood of his death. He came not only with the water, but with both the water and the blood. And the Spirit himself testifies that this is true, because the Spirit is truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">There are three witnesses:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">the Spirit, the water, and the blood; and all three give the same testimony.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">We believe human testimony; but God's testimony is much stronger, and he has given this testimony about his Son.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">So all who believe in the Son of God have this testimony in their own hearts; but those who do not believe God have made him out to be a liar, because they have not believed what God has said about his Son.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">The testimony is this: God has given us eternal life, and this life has its source in his Son.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">Whoever has the Son has this life; whoever does not have the Son of God does not have life.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I am writing this to you so that you may know that you have eternal life — you that believe in the Son of God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">We have courage in God's presence, because we are sure that he hears us if we ask him for anything that is according to his will.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">He hears us whenever we ask him; and since we know this is true, we know also that he gives us what we ask from him.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">If you see your brother or sister commit a sin that does not lead to death, you should pray to God, who will give them life. This applies to those whose sins do not lead to death. But there is sin which leads to death, and I do not say that you should pray to God about that.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">All wrongdoing is sin, but there is sin which does not lead to death.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">We know that none of God's children keep on sinning, for the Son of God keeps them safe, and the Evil One cannot harm them.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">We know that we belong to God even though the whole world is under the rule of the Evil One.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">We know that the Son of God has come and has given us understanding, so that we know the true God. We live in union with the true God — in union with his Son Jesus Christ. This is the true God, and this is eternal life.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">My children, keep yourselves safe from false gods!</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="64" bname="3  John">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">From the Elder — To my dear Gaius, whom I truly love. All your friends send greetings. Greet all our friends personally.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">My dear friend, I pray that everything may go well with you and that you may be in good health — as I know you are well in spirit.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">I was so happy when some fellow-Christians arrived and told me how faithful you are to the truth — just as you always live in the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">Nothing makes me happier than to hear that my children live in the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">My dear friend, you are so faithful in the work you do for your fellow-Christians, even when they are strangers.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">They have spoken to the church here about your love. Please help them to continue their journey in a way that will please God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">For they set out on their journey in the service of Christ without accepting any help from unbelievers.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">We Christians, then, must help these people, so that we may share in their work for the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">I wrote a short letter to the church; but Diotrephes, who likes to be their leader, will not pay any attention to what I say.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">When I come, then, I will call attention to everything he has done: the terrible things he says about us and the lies he tells! But that is not enough for him; he will not receive our fellow-Christians when they come, and even stops those who want to receive them and tries to drive them out of the church!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">My dear friend, do not imitate what is bad, but imitate what is good. Whoever does good belongs to God; whoever does what is bad has not seen God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">Everyone speaks well of Demetrius; truth itself speaks well of him. And we add our testimony, and you know that what we say is true.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I have so much to tell you, but I do not want to do it with pen and ink.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">I hope to see you soon, and then we will talk personally.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Peace be with you.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
</XMLBIBLE>
