<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<XMLBIBLE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" biblename="ENGLISH_CEB">
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="57" bname="Philemon">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">From Paul, a prisoner of the Anointed One, Jesus, and Timothy our brother, to Philemon, our precious friend and companion in this work.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">To the church that meets in his house, along with our dear sister Apphia and our fellow soldier Archippus.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">May God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ pour out his grace and peace upon you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">I am always thankful to my God as I remember you in my prayers</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">because I’m hearing reports about your faith in the Lord Jesus and how much love you have for all his holy followers.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">I pray for you that the faith we share may effectively deepen your understanding of every good thing that belongs to you in Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">Your love has impacted me and brings me great joy and encouragement, for the hearts of the believers have been greatly refreshed through you, dear brother.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Even though I have enough boldness in Christ that I could command you to do what is proper,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Formerly he was not useful or valuable to you, but now he is valuable to both of us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">He is my very heart, and I’ve sent him back to you with this letter .</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I would have preferred to keep him at my side so that he could take your place as my helper during my imprisonment for the sake of the gospel.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">However, I did not want to make this decision without your consent, so that your act of kindness would not be a matter of obligation but out of willingness.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Perhaps you could think of it this way : he was separated from you for a short time so that you could have him back forever.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">So welcome him no longer as a slave, but more than that, as a dearly loved brother. He is that to me especially, and how much more so to you, both humanly speaking and in the Lord.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">So if you consider me your friend and partner, accept him the same way you would accept me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">And if he has stolen anything from you or owes you anything, just place it on my account.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">I, Paul, have written these words in my own handwriting. I promise to pay you back everything, to say nothing of the fact that you owe me your very self.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">Yes, my brother, enrich my soul in the Lord—refresh my heart in Christ!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">I’m writing to you with confidence that you will comply with my request and do even more than what I’m asking.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">And would you do one more thing for me? Since I’m hoping through your prayers to be restored to you soon, please prepare a guest room for me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">Epaphras, my fellow prisoner in the Anointed One, Jesus, sends his greetings of peace to you,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">and so does Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, my companions in this ministry.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">May the unconditional love of the Lord Jesus, the Anointed One, be with your spirit!</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="63" bname="2  John">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">From the elder to God’s chosen woman and her children: I love you all as those who are in the truth. And I’m not the only one, for all who come to know the truth share my love for you</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">because of the living truth that has a permanent home in us and will be with us forever.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Grace, mercy, and peace belong to us, flowing from the presence of God the Father and from Jesus Christ, Son of the Father and from the realm of true love.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">I was delighted and filled with joy when I learned that your children are consistently living in the truth, just as we have received the command from the Father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Dearest woman, I have a request to make of you. It is not a new commandment but a repetition of the one we have had from the beginning: that we constantly love one another.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">This love means living in obedience to whatever God commands us. For to walk in love toward one another is the unifying commandment we’ve heard from the beginning.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">Numerous deceivers have surfaced from among us and gone out into the world, people who will not acknowledge Jesus Christ coming as a man. These deceivers are antichrists!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Be on your guard so that you do not lose all that we have diligently worked for but receive a full reward.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">Anyone who wanders away and does not remain faithful to the teaching of Christ has no relationship with God. But those who remain in the teaching of Christ have a wonderful relationship with both the Father and the Son.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">So if anyone comes into your fellowship claiming to be a true believer yet doesn’t bring this teaching, you are not to consider him as a fellow believer, nor should you welcome him into your homes.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">For if you welcome him as a believer, you will be partnering with him in his evil agenda.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">Although I have many more subjects I’d like to discuss with you, I’d rather not include them in this letter. But I look forward to coming to visit and speaking with you face-to-face —for being together will complete our joy!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">The children of your sister, whom God has chosen, send you their loving greetings. Amen.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="64" bname="3  John">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">From the elder to my dearly loved brother Gaius, whom I truly love:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Beloved friend, I pray that you are prospering in every way and that you continually enjoy good health, just as your soul is prospering.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">I was filled with joy and delight when the brothers arrived and informed me of your faithfulness to the truth. They told me how you live continually in the truth of Christ .</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">It is the greatest joy of my life to hear that my children are consistently living their lives in the ways of truth!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">My beloved friend, I commend you for your demonstration of faithful love by all that you have done for the brothers on their journey , even though they were strangers at the time.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">They have shared publicly with the congregation about the beautiful acts of love you have shown them. Now, if you would be so kind, send them on their way with a generous gift , in a manner that would honor God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">You see, it was their passion for the glory of the name of Christ that launched them out, and they’ve not accepted financial support from unbelievers.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">They are deserving of all the support we can give them, because through our giving we can partner with them for the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">I have already written you once about this, but Diotrephes, who loves to be in charge and recognized as first among you, does not acknowledge our authority.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">So if I come, I will address what he’s doing—spreading his malicious slander against us. And not content with that, he refuses to welcome our brothers, and he stands in the way of those who want to receive them and show them hospitality by throwing them out of the church!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Delightfully loved ones, don’t imitate what is evil, but imitate that which is good. Whoever does good is of God; whoever does evil has not seen God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">As for Demetrius, everyone speaks very highly of him, and even the truth itself stands by his side. We too wholeheartedly endorse him, and you know that our recommendation is reliable.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">Although I have many more subjects I’d like to discuss with you, I’d rather not include them in this letter.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">Instead, I hope to visit you and speak with you face-to-face.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Peace to you, my friend . Your friends here send their loving greetings to you. Please greet each one of our friends there by name.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
</XMLBIBLE>
