<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<XMLBIBLE xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" biblename="ENGLISH_AMP">
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="50" bname="Philippians">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Paul and Timothy, bond-servants of Christ Jesus (the Messiah, the Anointed), T o all the saints (God’s people) in Christ Jesus who are at Philippi, including the overseers and deacons: Y es, and I will rejoice [later as well],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Grace to you and peace [inner calm and spiritual well-being] from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">I thank my God in every remembrance of you,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">always offering every prayer of mine with joy [and with specific requests] for all of you,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">[thanking God] for your participation and partnership [both your comforting fellowship and gracious contributions] in [advancing] the good news [regarding salvation] from the first day [you heard it] until now.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">I am convinced and confident of this very thing, that He who has begun a good work in you will [continue to] perfect and complete it until the day of Christ Jesus [the time of His return].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">It is right for me to feel this way about you, because [you have me in your heart as] I have you in my heart, since both in my imprisonment and in the defense and confirmation of the good news [regarding salvation], all of you share in [His matchless] grace with me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">For God is my witness, how I long for all of you with the affection of Christ Jesus [whose great love fills me].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">And this I pray, that your love may abound more and more [displaying itself in greater depth] in real knowledge and in practical insight,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">so that you may learn to recognize and treasure what is excellent [identifying the best, and distinguishing moral differences], and that you may be pure and blameless until the day of Christ [actually living lives that lead others away from sin];</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">filled with the fruit of righteousness which comes through Jesus Christ, to the glory and praise of God [so that His glory may be both revealed and recognized].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">Now I want you to know, believers, that what has happened to me [this imprisonment that was meant to stop me] has actually served to advance [the spread of] the good news [regarding salvation].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">My imprisonment in [the cause of] Christ has become common knowledge throughout the whole praetorian (imperial) guard and to everyone else.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">Because of my chains [seeing that I am doing well and that God is accomplishing great things], most of the brothers have renewed confidence in the Lord, and have far more courage to speak the word of God [concerning salvation] without fear [of the consequences, seeing that God can work His good in all circumstances].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Some, it is true, are [actually] preaching Christ out of envy and rivalry [toward me—for no better reason than a competitive spirit or misguided ambition], but others out of goodwill and a loyal spirit [toward me].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">The latter [preach Christ] out of love, because they know that I have been put here [by God on purpose] for the defense of the gospel;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">but the former preach Christ [insincerely] out of selfish ambition [just self-promotion], thinking that they are causing me distress in my imprisonment.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">What then [does it matter]? So long as in every way, whether in pretense [for self-promotion] or in all honesty [to spread the truth], Christ is being preached; and in this I rejoice.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">for I know [with confidence] that this will turn out for my deliverance and spiritual well-being, through your prayers and the [superabundant] supply of the Spirit of Jesus Christ [which upholds me].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">It is my own eager expectation and hope, that [looking toward the future] I will not disgrace myself nor be ashamed in anything, but that with courage and the utmost freedom of speech, even now as always, Christ will be magnified and exalted in my body, whether by life or by death.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">For to me, to live is Christ [He is my source of joy, my reason to live] and to die is gain [for I will be with Him in eternity].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">If, however, it is to be life here and I am to go on living, this will mean useful and productive service for me; so I do not know which to choose [if I am given that choice].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">But I am hard-pressed between the two. I have the desire to leave [this world] and be with Christ, for that is far, far better;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">yet to remain in my body is more necessary and essential for your sake.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">Since I am convinced of this, I know that I will remain and continue with all of you for your progress and joy in the faith,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="26">so that your rejoicing for me may overflow in Christ Jesus through my coming to you again.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="27">Only [be sure to] lead your lives in a manner [that will be] worthy of the gospel of Christ, so that whether I do come and see you or remain absent, I will hear about you that you are standing firm in one spirit [and one purpose], with one mind striving side by side [as if in combat] for the faith of the gospel.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="28">And in no way be alarmed or intimidated [in anything] by your opponents, for such [constancy and fearlessness on your part] is a [clear] sign [a proof and a seal] for them of [their impending] destruction, but [a clear sign] for you of deliverance and salvation, and that too, from God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="29">For you have been granted [the privilege] for Christ’s sake, not only to believe and confidently trust in Him, but also to suffer for His sake,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="30">[and so you are] experiencing the same [kind of] conflict which you saw me endure, and which you hear to be mine now.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="2">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Therefore if there is any encouragement and comfort in Christ [as there certainly is in abundance], if there is any consolation of love, if there is any fellowship [that we share] in the Spirit, if [there is] any [great depth of] affection and compassion,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">make my joy complete by being of the same mind, having the same love [toward one another], knit together in spirit, intent on one purpose [and living a life that reflects your faith and spreads the gospel—the good news regarding salvation through faith in Christ].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Do nothing from selfishness or empty conceit [through factional motives, or strife], but with [an attitude of] humility [being neither arrogant nor self-righteous], regard others as more important than yourselves.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">Do not merely look out for your own personal interests, but also for the interests of others.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Have this same attitude in yourselves which was in Christ Jesus [look to Him as your example in selfless humility],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">who, although He existed in the form and unchanging essence of God [as One with Him, possessing the fullness of all the divine attributes—the entire nature of deity], did not regard equality with God a thing to be grasped or asserted [as if He did not already possess it, or was afraid of losing it];</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">but emptied Himself [without renouncing or diminishing His deity, but only temporarily giving up the outward expression of divine equality and His rightful dignity] by assuming the form of a bond-servant, and being made in the likeness of men [He became completely human but was without sin, being fully God and fully man].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">After He was found in [terms of His] outward appearance as a man [for a divinely-appointed time], He humbled Himself [still further] by becoming obedient [to the Father] to the point of death, even death on a cross.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">For this reason also [because He obeyed and so completely humbled Himself], God has highly exalted Him and bestowed on Him the name which is above every name,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">so that at the name of Jesus every knee shall bow [in submission], of those who are in heaven and on earth and under the earth,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">and that every tongue will confess and openly acknowledge that Jesus Christ is Lord (sovereign God), to the glory of God the Father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">So then, my dear ones, just as you have always obeyed [my instructions with enthusiasm], not only in my presence, but now much more in my absence, continue to work out your salvation [that is, cultivate it, bring it to full effect, actively pursue spiritual maturity] with awe-inspired fear and trembling [using serious caution and critical self-evaluation to avoid anything that might offend God or discredit the name of Christ].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">For it is [not your strength, but it is] God who is effectively at work in you, both to will and to work [that is, strengthening, energizing, and creating in you the longing and the ability to fulfill your purpose] for His good pleasure.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">Do everything without murmuring or questioning [the providence of God],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">so that you may prove yourselves to be blameless and guileless, innocent and uncontaminated, children of God without blemish in the midst of a [morally] crooked and [spiritually] perverted generation, among whom you are seen as bright lights [beacons shining out clearly] in the world [of darkness],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">holding out and offering to everyone the word of life, so that in the day of Christ I will have reason to rejoice greatly because I did not run [my race] in vain nor labor without result.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">But even if I am being poured out as a drink offering on the sacrifice and service of your faith [for preaching the message of salvation], still I rejoice and share my joy with you all.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">You too, rejoice in the same way and share your joy with me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">But I hope in the Lord Jesus to send Timothy to you soon, so that I may also be encouraged by learning news about you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">For I have no one else [like him who is] so kindred a spirit who will be genuinely concerned for your [spiritual] welfare.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">For the others [who deserted me after my arrest] all seek [to advance] their own interests, not those of Jesus Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">But you know of Timothy’s tested worth and his proven character, that he has served with me to advance the gospel like a son serving with his father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">Therefore, I hope [that it is His will] to send him immediately, just as soon as I see how my case turns out;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">and I trust [confidently] in the Lord that soon I also will be coming to you .</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">However, I thought it necessary to send back to you Epaphroditus, [who has been] my brother and companion and fellow soldier, who was also sent as your messenger to take care of my needs.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="26">For he has been longing for all of you and was distressed because you had heard that he was sick.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="27">He certainly was sick and close to death. But God had mercy on him, and not only on him but also on me, so that I would not have sorrow upon sorrow.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="28">So I have sent him all the more eagerly so that when you see him again you may rejoice and I may be less concerned about you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="29">Welcome him home in the Lord with great joy, and appreciate and honor men like him;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="30">because he came close to death for the work of Christ, risking his life to complete what was lacking in your service to me [which distance prevented you from rendering personally].</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="3">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Finally, my fellow believers, continue to rejoice and delight in the L ord . To write the same things again is no trouble for me, and it is a safeguard for you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Look out for the dogs [the Judaizers, the legalists], look out for the troublemakers, look out for the false circumcision [those who claim circumcision is necessary for salvation];</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">for we [who are born-again have been reborn from above—spiritually transformed, renewed, set apart for His purpose and] are the true circumcision, who worship in the Spirit of God and glory and take pride and exult in Christ Jesus and place no confidence [in what we have or who we are] in the flesh—</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">though I myself might have [some grounds for] confidence in the flesh [if I were pursuing salvation by works]. If anyone else thinks that he has reason to be confident in the flesh [that is, in his own efforts to achieve salvation], I have far more:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">circumcised when I was eight days old, of the nation of Israel, of the tribe of Benjamin, a Hebrew of Hebrews [an exemplary Hebrew]; as to the [observance of the] Law, a Pharisee;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">as to my zeal [for Jewish tradition], a persecutor of the church; and as to righteousness [supposed right living] which [my fellow Jews believe] is in the Law, I proved myself blameless.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">But whatever former things were gains to me [as I thought then], these things [once regarded as advancements in merit] I have come to consider as loss [absolutely worthless] for the sake of Christ [and the purpose which He has given my life].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">But more than that, I count everything as loss compared to the priceless privilege and supreme advantage of knowing Christ Jesus my Lord [and of growing more deeply and thoroughly acquainted with Him—a joy unequaled]. For His sake I have lost everything, and I consider it all garbage, so that I may gain Christ,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">and may be found in Him [believing and relying on Him], not having any righteousness of my own derived from [my obedience to] the Law and its rituals, but [possessing] that [genuine righteousness] which comes through faith in Christ, the righteousness which comes from God on the basis of faith.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">And this, so that I may know Him [experientially, becoming more thoroughly acquainted with Him, understanding the remarkable wonders of His Person more completely] and [in that same way experience] the power of His resurrection [which overflows and is active in believers], and [that I may share] the fellowship of His sufferings, by being continually conformed [inwardly into His likeness even] to His death [dying as He did];</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">so that I may attain to the resurrection [that will raise me] from the dead.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">Not that I have already obtained it [this goal of being Christlike] or have already been made perfect, but I actively press on so that I may take hold of that [perfection] for which Christ Jesus took hold of me and made me His own.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">Brothers and sisters, I do not consider that I have made it my own yet; but one thing I do: forgetting what lies behind and reaching forward to what lies ahead,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">I press on toward the goal to win the [heavenly] prize of the upward call of God in Christ Jesus.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">All of us who are mature [pursuing spiritual perfection] should have this attitude. And if in any respect you have a different attitude, that too God will make clear to you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">Only let us stay true to what we have already attained.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">Brothers and sisters, together follow my example and observe those who live by the pattern we gave you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">For there are many, of whom I have often told you, and now tell you even with tears, who live as enemies of the cross of Christ [rejecting and opposing His way of salvation],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">whose fate is destruction, whose god is their belly [their worldly appetite, their sensuality, their vanity], and whose glory is in their shame—who focus their mind on earthly and temporal things.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">But [we are different, because] our citizenship is in heaven. And from there we eagerly await [the coming of] the Savior, the Lord Jesus Christ;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">who, by exerting that power which enables Him even to subject everything to Himself, will [not only] transform [but completely refashion] our earthly bodies so that they will be like His glorious resurrected body.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="4">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Therefore, my fellow believers, whom I love and long for, my delight and crown [my wreath of victory], in this way stand firm in the Lord, my beloved.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">I urge Euodia and I urge Syntyche to agree and to work in harmony in the Lord.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Indeed, I ask you too, my true companion, to help these women [to keep on cooperating], for they have shared my struggle in the [cause of the] gospel, together with Clement and the rest of my fellow workers, whose names are in the Book of Life.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">Rejoice in the Lord always [delight, take pleasure in Him]; again I will say, rejoice!</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Let your gentle spirit [your graciousness, unselfishness, mercy, tolerance, and patience] be known to all people. The Lord is near.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">Do not be anxious or worried about anything, but in everything [every circumstance and situation] by prayer and petition with thanksgiving, continue to make your [specific] requests known to God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">And the peace of God [that peace which reassures the heart, that peace] which transcends all understanding, [that peace which] stands guard over your hearts and your minds in Christ Jesus [is yours].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Finally, believers, whatever is true, whatever is honorable and worthy of respect, whatever is right and confirmed by God’s word, whatever is pure and wholesome, whatever is lovely and brings peace, whatever is admirable and of good repute; if there is any excellence, if there is anything worthy of praise, think continually on these things [center your mind on them, and implant them in your heart].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">The things which you have learned and received and heard and seen in me, practice these things [in daily life], and the God [who is the source] of peace and well-being will be with you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">I rejoiced greatly in the Lord, that now at last you have renewed your concern for me; indeed, you were concerned about me before, but you had no opportunity to show it.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Not that I speak from [any personal] need, for I have learned to be content [and self-sufficient through Christ, satisfied to the point where I am not disturbed or uneasy] regardless of my circumstances.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I know how to get along and live humbly [in difficult times], and I also know how to enjoy abundance and live in prosperity. In any and every circumstance I have learned the secret [of facing life], whether well-fed or going hungry, whether having an abundance or being in need.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I can do all things [which He has called me to do] through Him who strengthens and empowers me [to fulfill His purpose—I am self-sufficient in Christ’s sufficiency; I am ready for anything and equal to anything through Him who infuses me with inner strength and confident peace.]</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">Nevertheless, it was right of you to share [with me] in my difficulties.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">And you Philippians know that in the early days of preaching the gospel, after I left Macedonia, no church shared with me in the matter of giving and receiving except you alone;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">for even in Thessalonica you sent a gift more than once for my needs.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">Not that I seek the gift itself, but I do seek the profit which increases to your [heavenly] account [the blessing which is accumulating for you].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">But I have received everything in full and more; I am amply supplied, having received from Epaphroditus the gifts you sent me. They are the fragrant aroma of an offering, an acceptable sacrifice which God welcomes and in which He delights.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">And my God will liberally supply (fill until full) your every need according to His riches in glory in Christ Jesus.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">To our God and Father be the glory forever and ever. Amen.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">Remember me to every saint in Christ Jesus. The brothers who are with me greet you.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">All God’s people wish to be remembered to you, especially those of Caesar’s household.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="53" bname="2  Thessalonians">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Paul, Silvanus (Silas), and Timothy, T o the church of the Thessalonians in God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Grace to you and peace [inner calm and spiritual well-being] from God the Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">We ought always and indeed are morally obligated [as those in debt] to give thanks to God for you, brothers and sisters, as is fitting, because your faith is growing ever greater, and the [unselfish] love of each one of you toward one another is continually increasing.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">Therefore, we speak of you with pride among the churches of God for your steadfastness [your unflinching endurance, and patience] and your firm faith in the midst of all the persecution and [crushing] distress which you endure.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">This is a positive proof of the righteous judgment of God [a sign of His fair verdict], so that you will be considered worthy of His kingdom, for which indeed you are suffering.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">For after all it is only just for God to repay with distress those who distress you,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">and to give relief to you who are so distressed and to us as well when the Lord Jesus is revealed from heaven with His mighty angels in a flame of fire,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">dealing out [full and complete] vengeance to those who do not [seek to] know God and to those who ignore and refuse to obey the gospel of our Lord Jesus [by choosing not to respond to Him].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">These people will pay the penalty and endure the punishment of everlasting destruction, banished from the presence of the Lord and from the glory of His power,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">when He comes to be glorified in His saints on that day [that is, glorified through the changed lives of those who have accepted Him as Savior and have been set apart for His purpose], and to be marveled at among all who have believed, because our testimony to you was believed and trusted [and confirmed in your lives].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">With this in view, we constantly pray for you, that our God will count you worthy of your calling [to faith] and with [His] power fulfill every desire for goodness, and complete [your] every work of faith,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">so that the name of our Lord Jesus will be glorified in you [by what you do], and you in Him, according to the [precious] grace of our God and the Lord Jesus Christ.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="2">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Now in regard to the coming of our Lord Jesus Christ and our gathering together to meet Him, we ask you, brothers and sisters,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">not to be quickly unsettled or alarmed either by a [so-called prophetic revelation of a] spirit or a message or a letter [alleged to be] from us, to the effect that the day of the Lord has [already] come.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Let no one in any way deceive or entrap you, for that day will not come unless the apostasy comes first [that is, the great rebellion, the abandonment of the faith by professed Christians], and the man of lawlessness is revealed, the son of destruction [the Antichrist, the one who is destined to be destroyed],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">who opposes and exalts himself [so proudly and so insolently] above every so-called god or object of worship, so that he [actually enters and] takes his seat in the temple of God, publicly proclaiming that he himself is God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Do you not remember that when I was still with you, I was telling you these things?</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">And you know what restrains him now [from being revealed]; it is so that he will be revealed at his own [appointed] time.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">For the mystery of lawlessness [rebellion against divine authority and the coming reign of lawlessness] is already at work; [but it is restrained] only until he who now restrains it is taken out of the way.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Then the lawless one [the Antichrist] will be revealed and the Lord Jesus will slay him with the breath of His mouth and bring him to an end by the appearance of His coming.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">The coming of the [Antichrist, the lawless] one is through the activity of Satan, [attended] with great power [all kinds of counterfeit miracles] and [deceptive] signs and false wonders [all of them lies],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">and by unlimited seduction to evil and with all the deception of wickedness for those who are perishing, because they did not welcome the love of the truth [of the gospel] so as to be saved [they were spiritually blind, and rejected the truth that would have saved them].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Because of this God will send upon them a misleading influence, [an activity of error and deception] so they will believe the lie,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">in order that all may be judged and condemned who did not believe the truth [about their sin, and the need for salvation through Christ], but instead took pleasure in unrighteousness.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">But we should and are [morally] obligated [as debtors] always to give thanks to God for you, believers beloved by the Lord, because God has chosen you from the beginning for salvation through the sanctifying work of the Spirit [that sets you apart for God’s purpose] and by your faith in the truth [of God’s word that leads you to spiritual maturity].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">It was to this end that He called you through our gospel [the good news of Jesus’ death, burial, and resurrection], so that you may obtain and share in the glory of our Lord Jesus Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">So then, brothers and sisters, stand firm and hold [tightly] to the traditions which you were taught, whether by word of mouth or by letter from us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">Now may our Lord Jesus Christ Himself and God our Father, who has loved us and given us everlasting comfort and encouragement and the good [well-founded] hope [of salvation] by His grace,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">comfort and encourage and strengthen your hearts [keeping them steadfast and on course] in every good work and word.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
		<CHAPTER cnumber="3">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Finally, brothers and sisters, pray continually for us that the word of the Lord will spread rapidly and be honored [triumphantly celebrated and glorified], just as it was with you;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">and [pray] that we will be rescued from perverse and evil men; for not everyone has the faith.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">But the Lord is faithful, and He will strengthen you [setting you on a firm foundation] and will protect and guard you from the evil one.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">We have confidence in the Lord concerning you, that you are doing and will continue to do the things [which] we command.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">May the Lord direct your hearts into the love of God and into the steadfastness and patience of Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">Now we command you, believers, in the name of our Lord Jesus Christ and by His authority, that you withdraw and keep away from every brother or sister who leads an undisciplined life and does not live in accordance with the tradition and teaching that you have received from us.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">For you yourselves know how you ought to follow our example, because we did not act in an undisciplined or inappropriate manner when we were with you [we were never idle or lazy, nor did we avoid our duties],</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">nor did we eat anyone’s bread without paying for it, but with labor and hardship we worked night and day [to pay our own way] so that we would not be a financial burden on any of you [for our support];</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">not because we do not have a right to such support, but [we provided our own financial support] to offer ourselves as a model for you, so that you would follow our example.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">For even while we were with you, we used to give you this order: if anyone is not willing to work, then he is not to eat, either.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Indeed, we hear that some among you are leading an undisciplined and inappropriate life, doing no work at all, but acting like busybodies [meddling in other people’s business].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">Now such people we command and exhort in the Lord Jesus Christ to settle down and work quietly and earn their own food and other necessities [supporting themselves instead of depending on the hospitality of others].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">And as for [the rest of] you, believers, do not grow tired or lose heart in doing good [but continue doing what is right without weakening].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">Now if anyone [in the church] does not obey what we say in this letter, take special note of that person and do not associate with him, so that he will be ashamed and repent.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Do not regard him as an enemy, but keep admonishing him as a [believing] brother.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">Now may the Lord of peace Himself grant you His peace at all times and in every way [that peace and spiritual well-being that comes to those who walk with Him, regardless of life’s circumstances]. The Lord be with you all.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">I, Paul, write you this final greeting with my own hand. This is the distinguishing mark in every letter [of mine, that shows it is genuine]. It is the way I write [my handwriting and signature].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with all of you.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="57" bname="Philemon">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">Paul, a prisoner [for the sake] of Christ Jesus (the Messiah, the Anointed), and our brother Timothy, T o Philemon our dearly beloved friend and fellow worker,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">and to [your wife] Apphia our sister, and to Archippus our fellow soldier [in ministry], and to the church that meets in your house:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Grace to you and peace [inner calm and spiritual well-being] from God our Father and the Lord Jesus Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">I thank my God always, making mention of you in my prayers,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">because I hear of your love and of your faith which you have toward the Lord Jesus and toward all the saints (God’s people).</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">I pray that the sharing of your faith may become effective and powerful because of your accurate knowledge of every good thing which is ours in Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">For I have had great joy and comfort and encouragement from your love, because the hearts of the saints (God’s people) have been refreshed through you, my brother.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Therefore [on the basis of these facts], though I have enough confidence in Christ to order you to do what is appropriate,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">yet for love’s sake I prefer to appeal to you —since I am such a person as Paul, an old man, and now also a prisoner [for the sake] of Christ Jesus—</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">I appeal to you for my [own spiritual] child Onesimus, whom I have fathered [in the faith] while a captive in these chains.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Once he was useless to you, but now he is indeed useful to you as well as to me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I have sent him back to you in person, that is, like sending my very heart.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I would have chosen to keep him with me, so that he might minister to me on your behalf during my imprisonment for the gospel;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">but I did not want to do anything without first getting your consent, so that your goodness would not be, in effect, by compulsion but of your own free will.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Perhaps it was for this reason that he was separated from you for a while, so that you would have him back forever,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="16">no longer as a slave, but [as someone] more than a slave, as a brother [in Christ], especially dear to me, but how much more to you, both in the flesh [as a servant] and in the Lord [as a fellow believer].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="17">So if you consider me a partner, welcome and accept him as you would me.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="18">But if he has wronged you in any way or owes you anything, charge that to my account;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="19">I, Paul, write this with my own hand, I will repay it in full (not to mention to you that you owe to me even your own self as well).</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="20">Yes, brother, let me have some benefit and joy from you in the Lord; refresh my heart in Christ.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="21">I write to you [perfectly] confident of your obedient compliance, since I know that you will do even more than I ask.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="22">At the same time also prepare a guest room for me [in expectation of a visit], for I hope that through your prayers I will be [granted the gracious privilege of] coming to you [at Colossae].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="23">Greetings to you from Epaphras, my fellow prisoner here in [the cause of] Christ Jesus,</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="24">and from Mark, Aristarchus, Demas, and Luke, my fellow workers.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="25">The grace of the Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="63" bname="2  John">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">The elder [of the church addresses this letter] to the elect (chosen) lady and her children, whom I love in truth—and not only I, but also all who know and understand the truth—</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">because of the truth which lives in our hearts and will be with us forever:</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">Grace, mercy, and peace (inner calm, a sense of spiritual well-being) will be with us, from God the Father and from Jesus Christ, the Father’s Son, in truth and love.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">I was greatly delighted to find some of your children walking in truth, just as we have been commanded by the Father.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Now I ask you, lady, not as if I were writing to you a new commandment, but [simply reminding you of] the one which we have had from the beginning, that we love and unselfishly seek the best for one another.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">And this is love: that we walk in accordance with His commandments and are guided continually by His precepts. This is the commandment, just as you have heard from the beginning, that you should [always] walk in love.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">For many deceivers [heretics, posing as Christians] have gone out into the world, those who do not acknowledge and confess the coming of Jesus Christ in the flesh (bodily form). This [person, the kind who does this] is the deceiver and the antichrist [that is, the antagonist of Christ].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">Watch yourselves, so that you do not lose what we have accomplished together, but that you may receive a full and perfect reward [when He grants rewards to faithful believers].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">Anyone who runs on ahead and does not remain in the doctrine of Christ [that is, one who is not content with what He taught], does not have God; but the one who continues to remain in the teaching [of Christ does have God], he has both the Father and the Son.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">If anyone comes to you and does not bring this teaching [but diminishes or adds to the doctrine of Christ], do not receive or welcome him into your house, and do not give him a greeting or any encouragement;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">for the one who gives him a greeting [who encourages him or wishes him success, unwittingly] participates in his evil deeds.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">I have many things to write to you, but I prefer not to do so with paper (papyrus) and black (ink); but I hope to come to you and speak with you face to face, so that your joy may be complete.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">The children of your elect (chosen) sister greet you.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
	<BIBLEBOOK bnumber="64" bname="3  John">
		<CHAPTER cnumber="1">
			<VERS vnumber="1">The elder [of the church addresses this letter] to the beloved and esteemed Gaius, whom I love in truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="2">Beloved, I pray that in every way you may succeed and prosper and be in good health [physically], just as [I know] your soul prospers [spiritually].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="3">For I was greatly pleased when [some of the] brothers came [from time to time] and testified to your [faithfulness to the] truth [of the gospel message], that is, how you are walking in truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="4">I have no greater joy than this, to hear that my [spiritual] children are living [their lives] in the truth.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="5">Beloved, you are acting faithfully in what you are providing for the brothers, and especially when they are strangers;</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="6">and they have testified before the church of your love and friendship. You will do well to [assist them and] send them on their way in a manner worthy of God.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="7">For these [traveling missionaries] went out for the sake of the Name [of Christ], accepting nothing [in the way of assistance] from the Gentiles.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="8">So we ought to support such people [welcoming them as guests and providing for them], so that we may be fellow workers for the truth [that is, for the gospel message of salvation].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="9">I wrote something to the church; but Diotrephes, who loves to put himself first, does not accept what we say and refuses to recognize my authority.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="10">For this reason, if I come, I will call attention to what he is doing, unjustly accusing us with wicked words and unjustified charges. And not satisfied with this, he refuses to receive the [missionary] brothers himself, and also forbids those who want to [welcome them] and puts them out of the church.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="11">Beloved, do not imitate what is evil, but [imitate] what is good. The one who practices good [exhibiting godly character, moral courage and personal integrity] is of God; the one who practices [or permits or tolerates] evil has not seen God [he has no personal experience with Him and does not know Him at all].</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="12">Demetrius has received a good testimony and commendation from everyone—and from the truth [the standard of God’s word] itself; and we add our testimony and speak well of him, and you know that our testimony is true.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="13">I had many things [to say when I began] to write to you, but I prefer not to put it down with pen (reed) and black (ink);</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="14">but I hope to see you soon, and we will speak face to face.</VERS>
			<VERS vnumber="15">Peace be to you. The friends [here] greet you. Greet the friends [personally] by name.</VERS>
		</CHAPTER>
	</BIBLEBOOK>
</XMLBIBLE>
